{"tossups": [{"question": "According to a legend about this man, he nearly stepped o5f a cli5f while near some brigands, but before he could fall, the opposite cli5f approached him, closing the gap. Another story holds that he earned the esteem of his peers by recognizing a mistake in a mezuzah. He claimed to have spiritually ascended to heaven, where he was told the Messiah would come when this man's teachings had been widely spread. This rabbi, whose teachings were collected by Jacob Joseph of Polonne (yah-kohb yoh-sef \"of \" poh-lohn-eh), led a populist movement that adopted the spiritual and joyful elements of kabbalistic teaching while ignoring some of its complex rules. He was criticized by rabbinical authorities for encouraging his followers to drink and dance and for going among the people dressed like them. This man is regarded as the founder of a sect that includes the o5fshoot Chabad and whose groups are led by a Rebbe. For 10 points, name this \"Master of the Good Name\" who founded Hasidic Judaism.", "answer": "Baal Shem Tov [or Rabbi Israel ben Eliezer; or Besht]", "category": "Religion"}, {"question": "This function is represented using the asterisk symbol in the Bird-Meertens (bird-MAIR-tenz) formalism. In Murray Cole's paper introducing algorithmic skeletons, he discusses this function as a way of implementing a \"minimal design\" principle. In Haskell, the fact that the order of multiple calls to this function does not matter forms the basis for a compiler optimization in which those calls to this function are \"jammed,\" similar to \"loop jamming.\" This function is used to generate a series of \"intermediate data groups\" in frameworks like CouchDB and Hadoop. In many functional languages, this function is similar to fold and filter, but it returns a list generated by applying an input function to an input list. For 10 points, name this higher-order function that is paired with \"reduce\" in the name of a model often used in Big Data.", "answer": "map [or morphism; prompt on arrow; do not accept \"MapReduce\" or \"reduce\"]", "subcategory": "Other Science", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "The upper right corner of a painting depicting this scene contains a sculpture of two hands, symbolizing the city of Antwerp, near an orange column containing guild symbols such as a bell and an X flanked by two vertical lines on each side. On the right of that painting, a man with a bucket bends over in a yard filled with oyster shells. An incident of almsgiving during this more general scene can be seen in the background of a still life containing a decapitated cow's head; that scene of a meat stall and this event was painted by Pieter Aertsen (AIRT-sen). A Bruegel painting of this scene contains two tiny salamanders symbolizing sin and the common motif of a pagan idol falling over during it. A semicircular canvas of this scene depicts the central group walking on the banks of a river and was painted by Annibale Carracci. An angel with its back to the viewer plays the violin in Caravaggio's depiction of a rest taken during this event. For 10 points, name this scene that depicts Mary, Joseph, and the baby Jesus fleeing from Herod.", "answer": "the Flight into Egypt [accept The Holy Family Giving Alms until \"almsgiving\"; accept Rest on the Flight into Egypt]", "subcategory": "Visual Fine Arts", "category": "Fine Arts"}, {"question": "This philosopher challenged the idea the equality is valuable in itself with what he called the \"Leveling Down Objection\" in his Lindley lecture, \"Equality and Priority.\" In another book, this philosopher identified five cognitive errors that lead people to believe acts affecting large numbers of people cannot be evaluated through consequentialism. This philosopher defined moral laws as those that were \"optimi3c, uniquely universally willable, and not reasonably rejectable,\" which is his \"Triple Theory\" of morality. This philosopher argued that person X at t1 and person Y at t2 were identical if they were related through \"relation R,\" which he illustrated with his teletransporter thought experiment. In his major work, this author of On What Matters probes utilitarianism for vulnerability to the \"mere addition\" paradox, a preference for a large population of less happy people. For 10 points, name this British philosopher whose Reasons and Persons describes the \"repugnant conclusion.\"", "answer": "Derek Parfit", "category": "Philosophy"}, {"question": "In a poem, this author wrote of a flower \"from some obliterated garden\" whose \"past existence magically lasts and glows forever in this poetry.\" In that poem by this man, the speaker celebrates how Destiny allows him to spare \"that silent flower, the very final rose that Milton held before his face, but could not see.\" This poet closed another poem by placing the title soldier in \"the Hell marked out for him by God,\" where \"the souls in purgatory of his soldiers and his horses\" march. This poet's \"A Rose and Milton\" and \"General Quiroga Rides to His Death in a Carriage\" were translated by Alastair Reid, who, like Norman Thomas di Giovanni, is one of his foremost translators. In thematic unity with many of his prose works, this poet wrote a poem noting that he \"had always thought of Paradise in form and image as a library.\" This author claimed that his \"Poem of the Gifts\" could have been written by Groussac in an essay about his blindness. For 10 points, name this Argentine poet better known for the stories collected in Ficciones.", "answer": "Jorge Luis Borges (HORE-hay loo-EES \"BOAR\"-hayce)", "subcategory": "World Literature", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "This group staged an early protest at a state capitol against the Mulford Act, and was often defended by attorney Charles Garry. Lesser-known members of this group included Geronimo Pratt, a veteran who adopted the last name \"Ji Jaga.\" A poster used by this group showed a man seated in a wicker chair carrying a rifle in one hand and a spear in the other. A member of this organization attacked a series of riots as \"Custeristic\" and formed alliances with Jose Cha Cha Jimenez's Young Lords and the Confederate flag-wearing Young Patriots. One member of this group wrote the autobiography Soledad Brother, and another was shot while drugged on his mattress in an FBI raid along with Mark Clark. This organization laid out the Ten-Point Program and managed the Free Breakfast for Children project. For 10 points, name this black radical organization founded by Huey Newton and Bobby Seale.", "answer": "Black Panther Party [or the BPP]", "subcategory": "American History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "One monarch of this name ordered a four-month-long bu5falo hunt that ended up killing 10,000 subjects and zero bu5falo. That same ruler of this name ordered the slave Jean Laborde to construct gigantic scissors to chop invaders in half. Rulers of this name were witnessed celebrating the domestication of zebu cattle with the \"Royal Bath\" at the fandroana (fahn-droh-ah-nah) festival. Joseph Gallieni put down the Menalamba rebellion a7ter exiling a leader of this name. Many traditional talismen called sampy were burned a7ter the conversion of the court of a monarch with this name. Christian converts living under a ruler of this name were made to drink poison as part of a trial by ordeal called the tangena; that ruler placed decapitated heads on pikes on the beach as part of her virulently anti-Christian stance and came to power a7ter possibly killing her husband Radama I. The establishment of a French colonial government in Antananarivo (an-tah-nah-nah-REE-voh) ended, for 10 points, the rule of the last of three queens of Madagascar with what name?", "answer": "Ranavalona [or Ranavalona I; or Ranavalona II; or Ranavalona III; do not accept \"Ravanalona\"]", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "Lighter lanthanides form ses\u00c2\u00b7qui\u00c2\u00b7oxides and chal\u00c2\u00b7co\u00c2\u00b7gen\u00c2\u00b7ides with this coordination number, and adopt a type-A structure, as opposed to a cubic type-C structure. A total orbital quantum number of this value is notated with the letter K in its term symbol. Compounds with this coordination number can rearrange themselves via the pseudo-rotational Bartell mechanism. A tetrahedral complex with this many d electrons will display similar, but lower, energy splitting patterns to a d\u00c2\u00b73 octahedral complex. Molecules with this coordination number can exist in a mono-capped trigonal prismatic or face-capped octahedral geometry. A state with spin three will have this number as its spin multiplicity. A complex with this coordination number is likely to exist in a D\u00c2\u00b75\u00c2\u00b7h symmetric geometry called pentagonal bi\u00c2\u00b7pyramidal. For 10 points, identify this coordination number which is also the number of f orbitals for a given energy level.", "answer": "seven", "subcategory": "Chemistry", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "Note to players: artist and type of work required. One of these paintings unusually shows St. John the Baptist with a cross made out of transparent crystal, instead of the conventional reed. That painting once formed the center panel of an altarpiece whose predella contained a lost panel showing St. Nicholas saving a ship during a storm, as well as a panel showing John the Baptist preaching. In addition to that painting for the Ansidei family chapel, these paintings include a work in which two children exchange a carnation. The background of that example is split by a pillar, so that the landscape is visible through two halves of separate arch windows. In another of these works, a throng of blue angelic faces appear behind the central 3gures, and two cherubs lean on their arms against the bottom. Saints Sixtus and Barbara appear with the title character of that work, which is partly titled \"Sistine.\" For 10 points, name these works by the artist of The School of Athens which, like the \"Aldobrandini\" one, depict the Virgin and her son.", "answer": "Madonnas by Raphael [accept any answers mentioning Madonnas by Raphael, or RaA\u0300faello Sanzio da Urbino]", "subcategory": "Visual Fine Arts", "category": "Fine Arts"}, {"question": "Sarah Brigham's 2016 revival of this play prefaces it with an hour-long monologue titled \"Jinny.\" A character in this play acquiesces to being called \"an old plant le7t over from the Edwardian wilderness\" a7ter arriving to pick up his daughter. A prop in this play supposedly prompted Pamela Lane to exclaim, \"Oh no! Not the ironing board.\" The protagonist of this play visits the mother of his friend Hugh in the hospital. This play contains a recurring motif involving two stu5fed animals symbolizing the central couple: a squirrel and a bear. This play's protagonist repeatedly blares on the trumpet from his room and berates the much kinder Welshman Cli5f. In this play, Helena Charles has a brief a5fair with the husband of her friend Alison, who su5fers a miscarriage before reconciling with that husband, Jimmy Porter. For 10 points, name this founding example of \"kitchen sink realism,\" a play by \"angry young man\" John Osborne.", "answer": "Look Back in Anger", "subcategory": "British Literature", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "During rehearsals for a performance of The Mute Girl of Portici in this city, a ballerina caught on 3re when her skirt accidentally brushed against a gas light. An opera house in this city pioneered the use of \"English traps,\" devices that allowed singers to quickly appear and disappear in order to resemble ghosts. Angered by the omission of an Act Two ballet scene, this city's \"Jockey Club\" disrupted the premiere of Richard Wagner's Tannha\u0308user (TAHN-hoy-zah); a7ter the opera ended, Wagner vowed to never stage works in this city again. In 1896, one of the counterweights of a chandelier in this city's opera house became dislodged and fell on a member of the audience. Most of Giacomo Meyerbeer's grand operas premiered in this city, which is the setting for a Francis Poulenc (poo-LAWNK) opera which ends with the executions of Mother Marie, Sister Constance, and a host of other Carmelite nuns. For 10 points, name this city where the poet Rodolfo lives in Puccini's La Bohe\u0300me.", "answer": "Paris", "subcategory": "Other Fine Arts", "category": "Fine Arts"}, {"question": "Loren Graham took the perspective of a member of this profession, Peter Palchinsky, in a history of the early Soviet Union titled for his \"ghost.\" Nikolai Bukharin earned popular scorn for a quote calling for the uni3cation of management with this profession. A famous member of this profession was the Jamaican-born Robert Robinson, whom the Soviet Union used in propaganda touting its anti-racism. In 1928, E3m Georgievich Evdokimov accused men of this profession in a North Caucasus town of communicating with emigre coal mine owners in the 3rst of Stalin's show trials. Joseph Stalin frequently quoted Yuri Olesha's formulation comparing writers to this profession with respect to human souls. The Shakhty Trial targeted men of this profession, whose representatives in the USSR included Artem Mikoyan and Igor Sikorsky. For 10 points, name these specialized workers in the Soviet Union who designed e5forts like the White Sea Canal.", "answer": "mechanical engineers [or aerospace engineers; prompt on scientists; prompt on answers like airplane designers]", "subcategory": "European History", "category": "History"}, {"question": " A nineteen-year-old composer with this surname won the Prix de Rome in 1913 by writing the cantata Faust et He\u0301le\u0300ne (eh-LEHN), only to die 3ve years later. A Romanian-born violinist who adopted the 3rst name George and this surname composed the showpiece \"Avant de mourir\" (ah-VAHN day moo-REER) A conductor with this last name revived interest in Monteverdi by recording many of his madrigals for the 3rst time in 1937, and later conducted the premiere of Stravinsky's Dumbarton Oaks concerto. A7ter the death of a composer with this surname, Lili, a related composer with this surname stopped writing music and started working at the American Conservatory in Fontainebleau (fohn-tahn-\"blow\"). That composer with this surname taught over 600 Americans, including Roy Harris, Virgil Thompson, and Aaron Copland. For 10 points, identify this surname of the French pedagogue Nadia.", "answer": "Boulanger (boo-lawn-ZHAY)", "subcategory": "Auditory Fine Arts", "category": "Fine Arts"}, {"question": "In 2007, researchers at UMich demonstrated that retinal regeneration in this organism occurs through dedi5ferentiation of Mu\u0308ller glia. Pancuronium bromide is used to study in vivo neuronal signaling in this organism. The use of this organism as a model was pioneered at the University of Oregon by George Streisinger. Irradiating sperm and applying hydrostatic pressure to the egg to disrupt the spindle during meiosis II (\"two\") can be used to generate par\u00c2\u00b7theno\u00c2\u00b7genetic, diploid examples of this organism. Ethyl\u00c2\u00b7nitroso\u00c2\u00b7urea was used in large forward-genetic screens to identify genes important in this organism's development by groups in Tu\u0308bingen and Boston. Transgenic examples of this organism can be generated with the Tol2 transposon system. This organism's Casper variant is transparent, and it is named for the stripes on its 6lanks. For 10 points, name this aquatic model organism, a freshwater fish.", "answer": "zebrafish [or D. rerio; or Danio rerio; or zebra danio]", "subcategory": "Biology", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "Citizens banished from this place asked Sparta for aid by pointing to a bag and saying \"The bag wants 6lour,\" to which the Spartans replied that the word \"bag\" was unnecessary. This place is not Arezzo, but Romans referred to bright-red clay pottery called terra sigillata as its \"ware.\" In 411 B.C., Alcibiades was recalled to this place as a radical democrat by Thrasybulus, who helped turn this place an Athenian government-in-exile opposed to the Four Hundred. Herodotus claims that the pharaoh Ahmose broke o5f Egypt's alliance with this city-state a7ter its tyrant discovered his lost ring in the belly of a 3sh. The engineer Eupalinos carved out a kilometer-long aqueduct in this place, which, along with its Heraion temple, was built under the tyrant Polykrates. Athens intervened against this island during its dispute with Miletus in a 440 B.C. war supposedly launched by Pericles to please the Milesian Aspasia. For 10 points, name this Greek island o5f the coast of Anatolia, the home of Pythagoras.", "answer": "Samos", "subcategory": "History Classical", "category": "History"}, {"question": "Rotoscoped archival footage of an event that took place in this city is interspersed with eyewitness interviews in a 2016 Kevin Maitland documentary. In the 1880s, this city was the home of a Jack the Ripper-style serial killer nicknamed the \"Servant Girl Annihilator.\" Visitors to this city o7ten take sel3es in front of a green wall with the words \"I love you so much\" painted on it. This city was the home of a thong-wearing, cross-dressing homeless man named Leslie Cochran who died in 2012. The \"Cathedral of Junk\" is in this city, which is the only remaining city to use moontowers for street lighting. Like Portland and Louisville, this city promotes itself with a slogan vowing to \"Keep [this city] Weird.\" The longest running American music television show is a PBS series named for this city's \"limits.\" For 10 points, name this city where South by Southwest takes place, the capital of Texas.", "answer": "Austin", "category": "Geography"}, {"question": "In a story in this collection, a woman brushes an ash from the back of a man's hand while telling him multiple times how \"wonderful\" and \"marvelous\" he was and repeating, \"God, I feel like an absolute dog!\" At the end of that story in this collection, a man accidentally drops a burning cigarette in his lap but angrily stops the woman in bed with him from snatching it up. In that story in this collection, the distressed Arthur recalls the title line from a poem that used to remind him of his wife while rambling over the phone to the gray-haired friend with whom she is cheating. The narrator addresses the title character and spells out the word \"faculties\" in the last line of another story in this collection. A man causes his companion to vomit by recalling how he shot a cat on the hood of a jeep in that story in this collection, in which a traumatized soldier relates how, a7ter completing his training in England prior to D-Day, he met the title precocious girl. For 10 points, name this collection including \"Pretty Mouth and Green My Eyes\" and \"For Esme\u0301\u00c2\u2014with Love and Squalor,\" a work of J. D. Salinger.", "answer": "Nine Stories", "subcategory": "American Literature", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "A de3nition of this quantity that takes the form of the Euler-Lagrange equations includes the expression \"the negative gradient\" of quantity \"scalar potential minus the dot product of velocity and vector potential,\" close quantity, minus \"the total derivative of vector potential.\" The divergence of the Maxwell stress tensor, minus the product of \"one over the speed of light squared\" and \"the time derivative of the Poynting vector,\" gives the value of this quantity in the continuum limit. The relativistic form of this quantity is proportional to the contraction of the contravariant electromagnetic 3eld strength tensor with the covariant four-velocity. In ideal magnetohydrodynamics, this quantity is decomposed into magnetic tension and magnetic pressure terms that produce circular motion around a guiding center. For 10 points, name this quantity that equals the sum of charge times the E-3eld and charge times the cross product of velocity with the B-3eld.", "answer": "Lorentz force [prompt on magnetic force or F; do not accept \"Abraham-Lorentz force\"]", "subcategory": "Physics", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "Peggy Sanday's ethnography about one of these places analyzes a masculine ritual she called \"the XYZ express.\" Mary Koss developed a widely-used survey to measure a major crime a7ter conducting a 1987 study of the inhabitants of these places. A 2002 study by David Lisak found that over 90 percent of a certain crime in these places was committed by \"serial\" o5fenders. A7ter Jeanne Clery was murdered in one of these places, the Clery Act was passed to require these places to disseminate annual security reports if they receive federal funding. The documentary The Hunting Ground examines the way they create victims like Lizzy Seeberg, who committed suicide a7ter reporting a crime that took place at one of them. In 2015, Rolling Stone retracted a Sabrina Rubin Erdely article about a crime committed in one of these places. For 10 points, name these places whose administrators frequently fail to investigate sexual assault complaints against athletes.", "answer": "colleges [or universities; or fraternities; prompt on schools]", "category": "Social Science"}, {"question": "This text narrates a war that begins when a peasant stones a sparrow that has been stealing his grain and ends when a slave kills the commander of the invading army with a pitchfork. In this text, a princess captured in battle avenges her father's death by convincing her drunken captor to wear a golden ornament around his neck, then using it to hang him on a tree while he is sleeping. This text claims that Odin ruled a country east of the Tanakvisl (tah-nah-KVIS-ul) river in Asia, but foresaw that his people would come to live in the northern part of the world. The brothers Eric and Alric kill each other with horse bridles in this text, which also tells the story of how Fjo\u0308lnir (FYOHL-neer) drowned in a vat of mead. This text is the 3rst section of a larger work that includes biographies of kings like Halfdan the Black and Olaf Tryggvason. For 10 points, identify this saga from the Heimskringla that chronicles a namesake Swedish dynasty said to have been founded by Freyr.", "answer": "Ynglinga (ING-ling[-uh]) saga [accept Heimskringla before \"section\"]", "category": "Mythology"}, {"question": "In a section of this poem written in quatrains, the speaker drinks the \"3ery wine\" of madness and sinks \"into the valley of the blind.\" This poem's speaker tells death, \"You will come in any case, so why not now?...I have turned o5f the lights and thrown the door wide open for you.\" The speaker recalls a time when \"only the dead smiled\" and a city swung like \"a needless appendage\" in this poem's \"Prologue.\" In a prose section at the beginning of this poem, \"something like a smile slip[s] across what had once been [the] face\" of a woman who whispers to the author, \"But can you describe this?\" as they stand in line outside a prison. This acmeist poem mourns the imprisonment of the author's son Lev Gumilev and the death of her husband Nikolai Punin under Stalinism. For 10 points, name this poem by Anna Akhmatova.", "answer": "Requiem [or Rekviem]", "subcategory": "European Literature", "category": "Literature"}], "bonuses": []}